{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this state, the book The Meritorious Price of Our Redemption was burned for heresy; its author, William Pynchon, founded this state’s town of Springfield. Edmund Andros was captured by rebels in what became this state in 1689, marking the end of the Dominion of New England. John Winthrop led a “Bay Colony” named after this state, which contains the site where the Pilgrims aboard the Mayflower established the Plymouth Colony. For ten points, name this state where colonists founded the city of Boston.",
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country established relations with Ethiopia’s Dawit II after settling the Swahili Coast. To defend against this country, the Sultanate of Oman built the Old Fort in Zanzibar. After the collapse of its Estado Novo, this country relinquished its colonies in Angola and Mozambique. For ten points, name this country whose caravel ships explored the world under Vasco de Gama and Henry the Navigator.",
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "question": "As part of this man’s business partnership with Bruce Sherman, he serves as CEO and oversees operations despite owning less than 5 percent of his team; as a result, he has received criticism for trading Marcell Ozuna and Giancarlo Stanton in the most recent Miami Marlins firesale. This man, who finished his playing career with the sixth most hits in history, became known as “Mr. November” for a clutch home run in 2001. For ten points, name this legendary shortstop for the New York Yankees who retired in 2014.",
      "answer": "Derek Jeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, reinforcements sent down the Hagerstown turnpike dissolved almost immediately when commander Joseph Mansfield was shot. After heavy fighting at Miller’s Cornfield, Dunker Church, and the Bloody Lane, the winning commander was criticized for failing to pursue his foes. The Emancipation Proclamation was issued shortly after this battle. George McClellan won at, for ten points, what 1862 battle in Maryland that proved to be the costliest single day in the Civil War?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Antietam",
        "Battle of Sharpsburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In an attempt to assassinate this ruler, Giuseppe Fieschi constructed a 25 barrel volley gun known as the Machine Infernale. This man’s Foreign Minister, Francois Guizot, fought with Lord Palmerston over the Spanish Queen Isabella II during the Affair of the Spanish Marriages. This King was frequently drawn as a pear by Honor´e Daumier [on-or-ay doh-me-ay]. This man came to power during the July Revolution and was overthrown in 1848. For ten points, name this French citizen king.",
      "answer": "Louis-Philippe I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The first known scientist to propose this theory was Aristarchus of Samos, who based his hypothesis on estimating the sizes of the objects involved. This theory, which argued in opposition to the Ptolemaic [toh-le-may-ik] model, was promoted in Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems, a book that led to Galileo’s house arrest. For ten points, name this astronomical theory proposed by Copernicus as a replacement for geocentrism.",
      "answer": [
        "heliocentrism",
        "word forms",
        "descriptions of “the Sun is at the center of the Solar System and/or Universe",
        "”",
        "descriptions of “the Earth or planets, etc. orbits the Sun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The author of this poem got his start composing literature when he saw a hunter kill a male crane in front of its mate. A woman in this poem uses one of two boons given to her by a king to order the king’s son into a fourteen-year exile in a forest. A ten-headed figure in this poem abducts a woman and holds her captive on the island of Lanka. Hanuman aids the title character in rescuing his wife Sita in, for ten points, what Indian epic poem often compared to the Mahabharata?",
      "answer": "Ramayana"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kenneth Bianchi was arrested in 1979 for committing two murders in Washington and 10 murders in this state as the “Hillside Strangler.” In this state, Elizabeth Short was murdered and her corpse severed in two in what became known as the Black Dahlia Murder. The symbol of a circle with a plus sign drawn through it was used by a murderer in this state who sent four ciphers to the police. For ten points, name this state where the Zodiac Killer terrorized San Francisco.",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "A palace in this region contained the Moorish Hall and Hall of the Singers, though neither of those were finished once the king mysteriously died in the waters of Lake Starnberg. In this region, a hill overlooking Hohenschwangau village was the site of a fortress that inspired the Sleeping Beauty castle, Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein]. The “Mad King” Ludwig II once ruled, for ten points, what German region whose capital is Munich?",
      "answer": "Bavaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1850s, Frederick Cumberland lost a conflict over a leadership position in this industry to Sandford Fleming. A milestone in this industry was celebrated in the town of Craigellachie. Hugh Allan received kickbacks in a scandal involving this industry, which toppled the government of John A. Macdonald. A company in this industry names the CN tower in Toronto. For ten points, name this industry that was involved in the Pacific Scandal and that completed a transcontinental connection across Canada in 1885.",
      "answer": "Canadian railroads"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Sangaku problem presented on a 1824 tablet in the Gunma prefecture concerns three of these shapes touching. These shapes were defined by Apollonius as the set of points in the plane that have a fixed ratio of distances to two foci. When Ferdinand von Lindemann proved that a certain constant is transcendental, he proved it is impossible to “square” one of these shapes. Line segments between two points on them are called chords. For ten points, name these shapes that have a constant radius.",
        "answer": "circles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lindemann proved that pi was transcendental in 1882, roughly a decade after this Swiss mathematician’s namesake number was proven transcendental by Charles Hermite. This man was patronized by Frederick the Great.",
        "answer": "Leonhard Euler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The death of Anne Fairfax led to ownership of this residence falling exclusively in the hands of its most famous inhabitant. In the 1850s, this building’s namesake Ladies’ Association bought it for preservation purposes. This house’s most famous resident lived here between the French and Indian War and Revolutionary War before being called on to become Commander-in-Chief of the Continental Army. For ten points, name this Virginia plantation owned by George Washington.",
        "answer": "Mount Vernon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of many replicas of Washington’s home at Mount Vernon was built for this organization in Seattle. Members of this group, which infamously refused to support a concert by Marian Anderson in 1939, must prove descent from an ancestor who assisted in American independence.",
        "answer": [
          "Daughters of the American Revolution",
          "DAR"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Recruitment posters for this war encouraging American soldiers to “Destroy this mad brute!” show an angry gorilla wearing a pickelhaube. During this war, which coincided with the Dada movement, John Singer Sargent painted blindfolded soldiers returning after being mustard gassed at the Battle of Ypres [eep]. The author of “Dulce et decorum est,” Wilfred Owen, died in, for ten points, what war that lasted from 1914 to 1918?",
        "answer": [
          "World War I",
          "the Great War",
          "the War to End All Wars"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another work of World War I-era literature is this novel by Erich Maria Remarque, in which Paul B¨aumer is urged to join the German army.",
        "answer": "All Quiet on the Western Front or Im Westen Nichts Neues"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Battle of Wuzhang Plains took place during this period and ended after the death of Zhuge Liang. A leader of this period was stunted at the Battle of Red Cliffs, which precipitated the rise of two rivals. Sima Yan established the Jin dynasty during this period by overthrowing the Cao Cao-founded Wei. The collapse of the Han dynasty led to, for ten points, what strife-filled period of Chinese history, named for the number of major combatants?",
        "answer": "Three Kingdoms period"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The tumult of the Three Kingdoms period essentially started in 184 AD with this peasant revolt, led by Zhang Jiao.",
        "answer": [
          "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
          "Yellow Scarves Rebellion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Duke of Ormonde oversaw Britain’s withdrawal from this war. After this war’s Battle of Denain, one side recovered much of its losses under the command of the duc de Villars. The duc de Tallard’s attempt to capture Vienna during this war was defeated at the Battle of Blenheim [blen-em]. The Duke of Marlborough and Eugene of Savoy commanded the winning alliance in this war against Louis XIV’s army. For ten points, name this conflict that ended when Philip V was recognized as king of a certain Iberian country.",
        "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the War of the Spanish Succession, the Duke of Ormonde was accused of treason for his alleged support of this 1715 uprising, which sought to restore the “Old Pretender” to the throne.",
        "answer": [
          "Jacobite rising of 1715",
          "Lord Mar’s Revolt"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One politician from this state refused to re-certify the President’s Surveillance Program from his hospital bed while serving as George W. Bush’s first Attorney General. This is the home state of John Ashcroft, as well as a Democratic Senate candidate who assembled an AR-15 rifle while blindfolded in a 2016 campaign ad; that man, Jason Kander, lost to incumbent Senator Roy Blunt. Claire McCaskill also serves, for ten points, what Midwestern state where Eric Greitens serves as governor in Jefferson City?",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mid-20th century politician served ten years as Senator from Missouri before serving less than three months as Vice President.",
        "answer": "Harry S Truman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region, Romans established the colonies of Narbo Martius and Massalia. In the third century BC, a group of people from this region settled in the Anatolian region of Galatia. Led by Brennus, an army from this region sacked Rome in 387 BCE. An Arverni king from this region, Vercingetorix, fought the Battle of Gergovia and the Siege of Alesia against Julius Caesar, who wrote commentaries on his conquest of this region. For ten points, name this ancient region in modern-day France.",
        "answer": "Gaul or Gallia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Julius Caesar’s commentaries on the Gallic Wars begin by stating that Gaul was divided into this many parts after his conquest.",
        "answer": "3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Architecture students at this university annually build a dragon and parade it through campus, though the dragon is no longer set ablaze. The namesake founder of this university founded the telegraph company Western Union. This private land grant university is located near Cayuga Lake, which is the longest of its state’s Finger Lakes. This school was founded 96 years after Dartmouth, making it the youngest Ivy League school. For ten points, name this prestigious university in Ithaca, New York.",
        "answer": "Cornell University"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This astronomer served as a professor at Cornell for almost three decades, during which time he compiled the Voyager Golden Record and wrote the book Cosmos.",
        "answer": "Carl Sagan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Cold War Spying",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Agency compromised by Robert Hanssen and earlier led by J. Edgar Hoover.",
          "answer": "FBI or Federal Bureau of Investigation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of Ethel and Julius, who were executed for giving American secrets to the USSR.",
          "answer": [
            "Ethel and Julius Rosenberg",
            "the Rosenbergs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of the Manhattan Project who was later accused of being a Communist spy.",
          "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police force headed by Erich Mielke that operated in East Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "Stasi",
            "Ministry for State Security",
            "Ministerium fur Staatssicherheit",
            "State Security Service",
            "Staatssicherheitsdienst",
            "MfS",
            "SSD"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American pilot released on the Bridge of Spies after his U2 spy plane was shot down over the USSR.",
          "answer": "Francis Gary Powers"
        },
        {
          "question": "US State Department official accused by Whittaker Chambers of hiding secrets in a pumpkin.",
          "answer": "Alger Hiss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ex-KGB officer who was poisoned with polonium in 2006 in London after his defection.",
          "answer": "Alexander Litvinenko"
        },
        {
          "question": "US counterintelligence program that decrypted Soviet messages, discovering the Cambridge Ring and exposing Klaus Fuchs.",
          "answer": "Venona Project"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of Stalingrad",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which the battle took place.",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "River on which Stalingrad lies, and which took the Germans three months to reach after starting the battle.",
          "answer": "Volga River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain range crossed by the German Army Group A to attack Baku, while Army Group B secured that river.",
          "answer": "Caucasus Mountains"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strategic resource sought by the Nazis in Case Blue, which attacked that mountain range.",
          "answer": "oil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Codename of the Soviet operation to encircle the enemy in Stalingrad, launched in November.",
          "answer": "Operation Uranus"
        },
        {
          "question": "German commander of the Sixth Army who surrendered to the Soviets, despite Hitler’s expectation.",
          "answer": "Friedrich von Paulus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Apartment building in central Stalingrad held by the Soviets for two grueling months.",
          "answer": "Pavlov’s House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tallest statue in Europe, built in 1967 to commemorate the battle.",
          "answer": "The Motherland Calls"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Non-Aligned Movement",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Only African country that is not a member, having gained its independence in 2011.",
          "answer": "South Sudan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Secretary General of the NAM, the President of Venezuela.",
          "answer": "Nicolas Maduro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Previous Secretary General of the NAM, the President of Iran.",
          "answer": "Hassan Rouhani"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only remaining European country in the NAM, led by Alexander Lukashenko.",
          "answer": "Belarus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that hosted the 1970 NAM conference in Lusaka under Secretary General Kenneth Kaunda.",
          "answer": "Zambia"
        },
        {
          "question": "1955 conference in Indonesia that inspired the founding of the NAM.",
          "answer": "Bandung Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of North Vietnam, the namesake of Vietnam’s largest city, who attended that conference.",
          "answer": [
            "Ho Chi Minh",
            "Ho Chi Minh City"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese premier who survived an assassination attempt en route to that conference.",
          "answer": "Zhou Enlai"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was banished to Avignon after Charles de Luynes caused the assassination of Concino Concini. This man allied France to Sweden via the Treaty of Barwalde in the (20 pts)",
        "Thirty Years’ War, countering Hapsburg power. This man, who defeated the Duke of Buckingham in the 1627 siege of (10 pts)",
        "La Rochelle, was targeted by Marie de Medici in the Day of the Dupes. For ten points, name this “Red Eminence,” an anti-Huguenot clergyman and chief minister to King Louis XIII [13th] who was succeeded by Cardinal Mazarin."
      ],
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu or Armand Jean du Plessis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carl and Louis Stokes, a pair of politicians from this state, testified before Congress after two railroad bridges were damaged near the Republic Steel Mill in an oil fire that inspired the creation of Earth Day. In the aftermath of that disaster, (20 pts)",
        "Time magazine claimed that a water source in this state was so polluted that one “does not drown [in it], but decay” after the polluted water (10 pts)",
        "caught on fire in 1969. For ten points, name this state where the Cuyahoga River “oozes” into Lake Erie after passing through Cleveland."
      ],
      "answer": "Ohio"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was the site of Operation Blue Bat, where Eisenhower sent 15,000 troops to help president Camille Chamoun end a religious war. To reduce ethnic conflicts in this country, its law mandates that its president must be a Sunni Muslim and its prime minister must be a (20 pts)",
        "Maronite Christian. This country was invaded in 2006 after Hassan Nasrallah organized numerous cross-border ambushes against (10 pts)",
        "Israeli villages. For ten points, name this country where Hezbollah is based in Beirut."
      ],
      "answer": "Lebanon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Crete was occupied by this power, which ruled the Kingdom of Negroponte in the Aegean Sea. This city-state lost the Battle of Agnadello to France during the War of the (20 pts)",
        "League of Cambrai. This city-state’s fort of Famagusta resisted the Ottoman siege of Cyprus, supported by a shipyard capable of mass-producing galleys, the (10 pts)",
        "Arsenale [ar-sen-ah-lay]. The Fourth Crusade was diverted to sack Zara and Constantinople by Enrico Dandolo, a doge [dohj] of this city. For ten points, name this northern Italian city-state built on a series of islands separated by canals."
      ],
      "answer": "Most Serene Republic of Venice"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, the losing side’s defensive lines were planned by engineer Richard Gridley. The third and final assault on the losing side’s redoubt led to the deaths of both John Pitcairn and Joseph (20 pts)",
        "Warren, and forced Isaac Prescott to withdraw from Charlestown. During this battle, Israel Putnam legendarily told his troops (10 pts)",
        "not to fire until they saw the whites of their enemies’ eyes. William Howe was victorious in, for ten points, what costly 1775 battle outside Boston fought near Breed’s Hill?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Robert Morrison’s translation of the Bible hastened the spread of Christianity in this country. The Nestorian Stone tells of how the monk Alopen traveled to this country, which was also visited by the Jesuit Matteo (20 pts)",
        "Ricci. The Three-Self Church was set up in this country when its communist party came to power in the early (10 pts)",
        "1950s. For ten points, name this country where Christianity was suppressed under the Cultural Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer wrote Carillon in response to the 1914 invasion of Belgium. This composer’s Coronation Ode, written for Edward VII, ends with a patriotic hymn whose melody was taken from the trio section of another work; that melody is (20 pts)",
        "“Land of Hope and Glory.” This composer depicted his publisher Augustus Jaeger as “Nimrod” in a piece with a hidden theme and wrote another work often played at (10 pts)",
        "graduations. For ten points, name this English composer of the Enigma Variations and the Pomp and Circumstance Marches."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Edward Elgar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Miguel de la Madrid was criticized for not allowing foreign aid after one of these events. The deadliest of these events in modern history struck Tangshan, China in 1976. The Marquis of Pombal cemented his power by rebuilding (20 pts)",
        "Lisbon after one of these events in 1755 caused widespread fires and a (10 pts)",
        "tsunami. Sixty-three people died in 1989 after one of these struck near Loma Prieta on the San Andreas fault. For ten points, name these natural disasters, one of which devastated San Francisco in 1906, that are commonly followed by deadly aftershocks."
      ],
      "answer": "earthquakes"
    }
  ]
}